ILR School Working Women's Institute Files /3099
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Institute for Education and Research on Women and Work records
1971-1986
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations (NYSSILR)
Institute for Education and Research on Women and Work
/3099
1 cubic feet
1 linear ft.
Records (documents).
Consists of course manuals, workshop handbook,s event programs, and newsletters on women in trade unions.
6179208
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, July 01, 2014
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, February 22, 2019
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: /3099m: ILR School Proposal for a Working Women's Institute for Research and Education 5583/5: Archives Organization File (AOF) Part 5
Scope and Contents
The Institute for Education and Research on Women and Work records contains course manuals, workshop handbooks, and event programs, 1961-1994 (bulk 1971-1983). Subjects include women in American labor history, leadership psychology, assertiveness, personal finance, and maternity/pregnancy provisions. Though the majority of the collection reflects the program's operations in New York City, folders 5 and 6 document similar operations at the Buffalo and Rochester Extension offices. Also contains handouts, brochures, and bulletins on sexual harassment in the workplace from the Working Women's Institute.
Biographical / Historical
The Institute of Education and Research on Women and Work grew out of the Trade Union Women's Studies program, founded in 1973 and operated out of the NYSSILR Metropolitan office in New York City. In 1971, the Metropolitan office began responding to the growing needs of working women by offering experimental seminars like "Womanpower: A New Voice in Union and Community." A Ford Foundation grant in 1972 funded a pilot study conducted by the Metropolitan office, which revealed educational and social barriers to women's participation in unions. Consequently, Trade Union Women's Studies was established in 1973 with Barbara Wertheimer and Anne Nelson serving as the program's first Director and Associate Director, respectively.
Trade Union Women's Studies became a research center and resource for working women, organizing workshops, short courses, seminars, and conferences in New York City, Rochester, and Buffalo. A year-long reserve credit program designed for union women, an alternate first-year track in Cornell's two-year Labor/Liberal Arts Certificate Program, launched in fall of 1974, offering courses in communication, labor history, and leadership. In 1975, the program renamed itself Working Women's Program for Research and Education and expanded their reach, developing a statewide education network linking business and labor unions with two and four-year institutions and planning a national training program in arbitration and mediation for women and minorities with Professor Jean McKelvey. In 1977, NYSSILR approved Wertheimer and Nelson's proposal to establish the Institute for Education and Research on Women and Work to continue the program. The Institute remained active into the mid-1980s.
New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations.
6179208
- Workshops and conferences, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes planning materials, correspondence, and handwritten notes for two conferences: "Womanpower - A New Voice in Union and Community" (1971), "Womanpower - A New Voice in Union and Community II" (1971) and "Women and Unions" (1972).
- Course: Women in American Labor History, 1975-1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Also includes course outline for "Maternity and Pregnancy Provisions US and Abroad" by Jeanne M. Stellman, PhD
- Trade Union Women's Studies program and events, 1961, 1970-1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Includes. promotional materials for the program. Also includes Includes conference and seminar material on women and money, women and law, and career development.
- Introduction to Collective Bargaining, 1976-09 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Course outline prepared by Francine Herman
- Central District Extension Division, Women's Education and Development Committee, 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Contains memos, clippings workshop advertisements, and the 1978-1979 Rochester Career Development Women's Studies handbook
- Buffalo Labor Studies program, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Workshop handbooks, 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Contains Trade Union Women's Studies workshop handbooks for "Mathematics of Work" (April 1976, Barbara Stern-Coder), "Psychology of Leadership" (Spring 1976, Anne H. Nelson); Institute for Education and Research on Women and Work workshop handbooks for "E
- Workshop handbooks, 1974-1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Contains Trade Union Women's Studies workshop handbook for "Women in American Labor History" (March 1974, Louise Mitchell) and Institute for Education and Research on Women and Work workshop handbooks for "Parliamentary Procedure (September 1978).
- Writing and Study Skills, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  12 session course for Women's First Year Labor/Liberal Arts program.
- Courses, workshops, conference materials, 1974-1986 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- 100 Years of Women in the Workforce, 1975-09 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Course handbook by Louise Pearson Mitchell
- Manual on Union Organization and Administration, 1981-12 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Revised course handbook by Barbara Wertheimer
- Social Behavior and Work, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Course handbook by Anne H. Nelson
- Writing and Study Skills, 1974-09 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Course handbook by Constance Taber Colby
- Working Women's Institute, 1975-1983 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Includes handouts and survey on how to deal with sexual harassment and Working Women's Institute brochures.
- Working Women's Institute, 1977-1994 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Contains articles by or citing members of the Working Women's Institute (WWI) and WWI digests and legal briefs. Also includes the testimony of the WWI and the Women's Legal Defense Fund before the Subcommittee on Labor-Management Relations of the House Co
- Indiana University, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Contains narrative report and instruction materials from "Leadership Training for Trade Union Women" grant project and correspondence from Suzanna Maffei, Project Director, Indiana University Division of Labor Studies, to Barbara Wertheimer.
- Enhancing Your Test Taking Abilities: A Manual for Administrative Employees in NYS Service, 1979-08 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Manual for course
- Strategies for New Health Delivery Services for Unions and Communities, 1974-08-19-1974-08-20 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Proceedings of the National Conference
- Working Women's Institute, 1983-1986 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Working Women's Institute research bulletins and reports., 1975-1982 (Box 1, Folder 21)